Guide to the Papers of Henry Santiestevan, 1975-2012 M1868
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
Henry Santiestevan Papers
1975-2012
M1868
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
4.5 Linear feet
Reports, memorandums, meeting minutes, pictures, invoices, grant proposals, press releases, newspaper clippings, notes, correspondence with prominent Mexican American civil rights and labor figures. Also contains various copies of Santiestevan’s resumes, work applications, writings for magazines, journal articles, and letters of recommendation supporting the hiring of Santiestevan. Numerous documents pertaining to the management of his public relations firm, Santiestevan & Associates.
Santiestevan, Henry
Santiestevan, Stina
Biography
Henry Santiestevan was born Enrique Santiestevan on July 7, 1915 in Nogales, Sonora, Mexico. Henry is English for Enrique. His parents were Enrique J. Santiestevan and Maria Victoria Morel Santiestevan. His wife was Marystina Ellen Sternlov Santiestevan. Santiestevan graduated from John H. Francis Polytechnic High School in Los Angeles, California in 1934. Due to an illness his entrance into Occidental College was postponed. He graduated from Occidental college in 1940. Between 1943 and 1946 he served in the US Army and was honorably discharged in 1946. After his service in the US Army he went to work for the Hollywood-Citizen News. Eventually he would join the CIO and run its Western edition of the CIO news as its editor. In the late 1940s he became politically active and assisted Ed Roybal in becoming the first Mexican American elected to the Los Angeles City Council.
Mr. Santiestevan would go on to serve as the President of the Newspaper Guild and became a political director for the CIO in Los Angeles. In 1958 he took a position with United Auto Workers (UAW) and worked alongside their President, Walter Reuther. Later Mr. Santiestevan would become the editor of Solidarity the monthly magazine of the United Auto Workers, and Agenda with the Industrial Union Department. Through Mr. Santiestevan’s position as an editor he became a close confidant of labor organizer Cesar Chavez and assist with public relations and media campaigns for the United Farm Workers.
In 1970 Mr. Santiestevan became the director of the Southwest Council of La Raza (SWCLR) today’s National Council of La Raza (NCLR). After leaving SWCLR he established his own public relations consulting firm. He had numerous clients from across the country and was revered as a prominent writer. He retired in 1997. Mr. Santiestevan passed away on January 22, 2000.
Stanford also holds over eight hours of recorded interviews by Yale historian Stephen Pitti. Pitti was a doctoral candidate at Stanford when he conducted the interviews. They are located in the Special Collections department at Stanford University.
Access to Collection
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Acquisition Information
This collection donated by Henry Santiestevan to Stanford University, Special Collections in December, 2011.
AFSCME.; Alatorre, Richard; Babbitt, Bruce, Governor; Chavez, Cesar, 1927-1993; Hispanic Policy Development Project.; Kennedy, Robert F., 1925-1968, --Friends and associates; Labor Council for Latin American Advancement; Mexican American Legal Defense and Educational Fund; National Opinion Research Center.; Reuther, Walter, 1907-1970; Samora, Julian, 1920-; Santiestevan Associates.; Santiestevan, Henry; Santiestevan, Stina; Southwest Council of La Raza.; Southwest Voter Registration Education Project. (U.S.); Spanish speaking social action council.; United Farm Workers; Velázquez, Willie
- American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees (AFSCME) (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Labor Council for Latin Ameircan Advancement (LCLAA): Memos and newspaper clippings (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Labor Council for Latin American Advancement (LCLAA): Correspondence and newsletters circa 1995 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Hispanic Policy Devlelopment Project (HPDP): Meeting of the Board of Directors 1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Hispanic Policy Development Project (HPDP) includes by-laws (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Hispanic Policy Devlelopment Project (HPDP) (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Hispanic Policy Devlelopment Project (HPDP) (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Hispanic Policy Devlelopment Project (HPDP) Memo to Siobhan O.Nicolau (Box 2, Folder 3)
- The Hispanic Policy Development Project (HPDP): Contracts (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Industrial Union Department (IUD) (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Industrial Union Department: Memos and Reports (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Industrial Union Department: Correspondence 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- An Initial Proposal to the Department of Housing and Urban Development (Box 2, Folder 8)
- IUD Agenda, June 1967 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- United Farm Workers (UFW): Photographs and Clippings (Box 3, Folder 1)
- 1986 Edward R. Murrow selection Committee (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Harvard Law School Center for Criminal Justice: 1975, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Santiestevan Associates: 1982-1993 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Miscellaneous Material: Resume and Correspondence: 1988-1994 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Southwest Voter Registration Project: A Project Director's Handbook, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Citizens Participation Project, Board Meeting, March 1986 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- A Communication Strategy for the Hispanic Policy Project: 1982 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Southwest Voter Registration Edcuation Project. 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Identity, Assimilation and The Social Question: The Mexican Americans in Los Angeles by Jennifer Hurstfield. 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- The Empleo Organization. 1967 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Santiestevan Associates (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Instant Aliens in their own land. A Report on Chicano Organizational Development by Henry Santiestevan (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Henry Santiestevan Vs Sports Committee. 1976 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Ford Foundation Contract (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Ford Foundation Proposal. 1974 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Hispanic Policy Development Project. 1982 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Santiestevan Associates Correspondence 1979 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- The Role of the Undocumented Alien in Small Business in Region IX. (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Mexican American Political Association 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- National Hispanic Reporter article with picture. 1991. (Box 4, Folder 11)
- National Opinion Research Center 1982 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- National Opinion Research Center 1982 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Crusade for Justice, I am Joaquin (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Community Service Organization (CS) 1980 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Changing Relations (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Changing Relations (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Changing Relations (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Changing Relations (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Mexican American Legal Defense and Education Fund 1967 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- The Missing Half. Correspondence with William Velasquez. (Box 5, Folder 6)
- The Missing Half Board Meeting. March 1987 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Marine corporal William Gallegos (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Eric Simon, Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Santestevan Associates (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Spanish Radio 1982 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Creative Identity 1992 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- The Weatherhead Foundation. Aspen conference. August 1972 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- La Raza Unida 1968 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- National Latino Communications Center 1992 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Ted Kennedy Campaign 1979 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Spanish Speaking Social Action Council 1967 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Spanish Speaking Social Action Council (Box 6, Folder 5)
- The Office of The United States Permanent Representative to UNESCO (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Hispanics in Education: 1986 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Wire to Cesar Chavez; 1968 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Santiestevan Column: Me and Jack (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Bobby Kennedy Campaign (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Santiestevan and Associates (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Ted Kennedy Campaign: 1979 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Early Resume (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Congress of Industrial Organizations: 1950-1957 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Mexican Americans and Labor Organizations, Jobs and Income by Henry Santiestevan (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Correspondence with Julian Samora. 1979 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Henry Santiestevan, montly colmns. 1991 (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Santiestevan Associates (Box 6, Folder 18)
- Press Release. Round the clock vigil to mark the end of Cesar Chavez's fast. March 1968 (Box 6, Folder 19)
- A Perspective on Mexican American Organizations, by Henry Santiestevan. September 1975. (Box 6, Folder 20)
- Columb by Henry Santiestevan. Twisted Logic: 1992 (Box 6, Folder 21)
- Report to the Second Constitutional Convention: August 1975 (Box 6, Folder 22)
- Southwest Voter Registration Project: 1988-1979 (Box 6, Folder 23)
- Inequality, Jobs, Income and Latinos. By Henry Santiestevan. (Box 6, Folder 24)
- A Brief look at Hispanic Union History (Box 7, Folder 1)
- A call to la raza for a personal pledge to Non-Violence (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Correspondence with Bruce Babbitt, Governor of Arizona (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Ford Foundation Grant Application, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Labor Council for Latin American Advancement, Alameda County Chapter (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Labor Council for Latin American Advancement, August 1996 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Industrial Union Department (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Letter requesting Baptism certificate (Box 7, Folder 8)
- AFSCME (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Personal Qualifications Statement :Office of Management and Budgett Approval (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Miscellaneous Photographs (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Obreros Unidos, Workers United, Correspondence, printed material (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Hispanic Policy Development Project, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- MISCELLANEOUS PUBLICATIONS: Deinstitutionalization, Out of their beds and into the streets; LCLAA at FIFTEEN; Early Childhood Development (two variant copies); Windows of Opportunity, Volume I and Volume II; Cinco Anos; Hispanic Policy Development Project, Multiple volumes, The Hispanic Almanac, 2nd edition; Organize Today, Officers' Report, 1986; Closing the Gap for U.S. Hispanic Youth, 1998; Make Somthing Happen, Volume I; Three Aspects of Diversity, 1995; Equitable Access, 1996, Miscellaneous Brochures (Box 9)